today we are going to talk about a
magical HTML element that has been
around for a long time but that not many
of us know about or use thanks to this
element we can make our website a lot
faster just by writing a few lines of
code that element is the picture element
and if you use it well it can do wonders
for you it is crazy to me that this
element is not used more often it is
supported by all major browsers so there
is really no excuse for not using it as
you can guess the picture element is
used to display images in our website I
know what you're thinking we already
know how to put pictures on a website
all we have to do is use the image
element well that might be true the
image element is kind of old and the web
and its users have evolved a lot we now
have devices of all sizes and kinds
users on Wi-Fi and mobile networks some
with fast and some with slow speeds and
we also have new and better image
formats like web P jpeg XL and and avaf
what this means for us developers is
that we have to optimize our websites as
much as we can we have to be mindful
about screen sizes browser support file
sizes download speed and more having
said this if you don't use the picture
element and you stick to the image
element there are still a couple of
things that you can do to optimize the
way your image is load so let's start
from there let's say we have an image in
our website and we want to optimize the
way it loads the first thing we can do
is change how and when the image is
loaded by the browser we do this by
setting the attribute loading to be lazy
what this does is it tells the browser
that you do not want to load your image
right away but rather only when the user
is actually going to see it in this
example we can see how as the user
Scrolls on the network panel the browser
is fetching each image one by one
instead of loading all of them at the
same time that is awesome this way you
only load the images that your user is
actually going to see you don't have to
write any JavaScript to enable this
feature all you need to do is set the
loading attribute to lazy and you are
good to go the browser will detect when
the image is about to enter the screen
of the user and we load it automatically
without the user seeing a blank square
or a loading image lazy loading can make
your website a lot faster but we must
think about the picture sizes we are
giving to our users even with lazy
loading if the images and their sizes
are not optimized the website will load
slow thankfully the image element allows
us to choose when to show a high
definition image to our users and when
to show a smaller one so that we give
our users only the images they need this
is by using the source set and the sizes
attributes Source said allows us to
Define different images to be loaded on
different devices based on screen size
resolution or type of device you using
Source set we can load a smaller low
resolution image on a mobile device with
a small screen but a larger high
definition image on a desktop computer
with a big screen Source set makes your
website load faster because it allows
each device to load the most suitable
image on this example we are using
Source set to tell the browser that we
have an image called cut small.jpg that
is 500 pixels wide a cut medium.jpg that
is a thousand pixels wide and a cut
large JPEG that is 2 000 pixels wide we
are also using the source attribute
which acts like a default in case the
user is on a browser that does not
support source which is almost never
going to happen since sources is
supported by 90 of all browsers as you
can see on the code all we are doing is
communicating to the browser that we
have three different versions of the
same image and stating their sizes it is
then the browser job to choose which
image to load if the user is on a small
screen on a mobile device the browser
will choose to load the smallest image
and if the user is on a desktop screen
the browser will load the biggest one
the image is also chosen depending on
the pixel density of the screen meaning
that if the user is on a device with an
HD screen like a retina display Apple
computer the browser might choose to
load the highest resolution image so the
user doesn't see a blurry one to help
the browser decide which image to load
from The Source set we can use the sizes
attribute with the sizes attribute we
can give the browser extra information
about how the image will be displayed on
different screen sizes this is how it
works here we are telling the browser
that if the viewport width is 600 pixels
or less the image will display at 400
pixels wide if the viewport is between
601 and 1200 pixels the image will
display at 800 pixels wide and for
viewports larger than 12 100 pixels the
image will display at 1400 pixels wide
then the browser uses this information
along with the widths provided by The
Source set attribute to choose the most
suitable image to load as you can see
the image element is very powerful and
it can help us optimize a loading speed
if we use it with the correct attributes
with the image element we just give
information to the browser and the
browser is the one that makes the
decision on which image to load If
instead of that you want to have all
control and you want to be the one
choosing which image to load and when
you can use the picture element the
picture element itself isn't exciting at
all what's exciting is what you put
inside of it inside of the picture
element we can put many Source elements
the browser will look at each one of the
source elements and display the one that
matches the conditions that you specify
like in this example here we have a
picture element with two Source elements
inside of it the First Source tag points
to the image cut
vertical.jpg which will be used when the
device orientation is Portrait the media
attribute orientation portrait specifies
this condition the Second Source tag
points to the image cut
horizontal.jpg which will be used when
the device orientation is landscape this
is specified by the media attribute
orientation landscape finally there is
an image tag with the SRC attribute set
to cut default.jpg this acts as a
fallback and will be used if neither of
the conditions of the source Stacks are
met or if the browser doesn't support
the picture and Source stacks on the
media attribute of the source element we
can write any CSS media query we want we
could for example show a different image
depending on the size of the screen of
the user we can show a different image
based on dark mode or light mode we can
load images depending on the resolution
of the screen remember on the media
attribute you can write the media query
is you would write on CSS so you can
show different images depending on
screen height or you could combine the
media queries as well like here where we
are loading images depending on both the
screen orientation and width of the
device we can also use the source
element to load images depending on
their file format like on this example
where the browser will try to load the
jpeg XL image first if it can support or
find the format it will attempt to load
the webp image next if that also isn't
supported it will then try the avif
image if none of these formats are
supported or found it will finally load
the jpeg image as a folder jpeg Excel
webp and avif are all fairly new image
formats jpeg Excel has better
compression and is designed to replace
the jpeg PNG and GIF although it's not
supported by most browsers webp is
developed by Google it's fairly well
supported and is also designed to
replace jpeg PNG in GIF according to
Google the average web P file size is 25
to 34 percent smaller compared to a JPEG
file of equivalent quality avif is
derived from the av-1 video Codec in
some tests avif has been able to save 50
on file sizes compared to jpeg with
similar perceptual quality avif also
supports animation so it can replace
gifs and it supports transparent images
which means it can replace pngs it is
not as well supported as webpable is
getting there and that's it for this
video you now know how to make your
website faster and more responsive you
are now equipped to handle different
screen sizes and network speeds and file
formats like a pro so go ahead
experiment with these new tools and see
the difference they make if you found
this video useful please consider liking
it and subscribing to the channel and
don't forget that if you want to learn
things like JavaScript python react
react native gold Dart flutter among
many many others for absolutely free all
you have to do is click the link below
to join any of our many free courses
that you can take right now for
absolutely free with me click the link
below and I will see you there alone
see you on the next one bye
foreign
[Music]